[Music]
all right
and welcome to actin flab live stream
number 39.1 it's march 2nd 2022
welcome to the actin flap we're a
participatory lab that is communicating
learning and practicing applied active
inference
this is recorded in an archive live
stream please provide feedback so we can
improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and will follow good
video etiquette for live streams
to learn more about actin flap go to
activeinference.org
we're here in active stream number 39.1
and we are learning and discussing this
paper
morphogenesis as bayesian inference a
variational approach to pattern
formation and control in complex
biological systems by coochling fristen
georgiev and levin from 2020
and we had a
fun
dot zero and time probably all
individually going through the paper
pretty much in
thirty nine one we'll just kind of go
over introductions and then can go to
a blank
page and just see where especially
stephen
and blue want to raise any questions and
also anyone can ask in the live chat
okay so
we'll just do introduction so i'm daniel
i'm a researcher in california and i'll
pass it to liv
i'm blue i'm a researcher in new mexico
and i will pass it to stephen
hello i'm stephen sillett i'm based in
toronto i'm a sort of a
action researcher and practitioner in
community development and participatory
theater and i will pass it to dean
good morning i'm dean i'm here in
calgary um
and not much to say other than i'm kind
of looking forward to hearing what uh
what blue and steven have to add to this
uh
this rather uh
big math question and how that fits with
morphology so
back to you dan
okay
um
well
if anyone wants to start with
a specific
question or figure or we can review
just sort of the
main points of the paper like let's look
at the roadmap
so
what section would people like to enter
in or have a question or idea related to
or we can just go yeah dean
so
you wanted to talk about this and i
wanted to talk about this and
it was it was this whole section on the
least action principle which i think we
both find quite
interesting because
yeah
why
um
and
it led me to the question of is there is
there something efficient about search
over
somebody sort of passing along and
sharing so i'm kind of curious what
people
think of that in terms of the math and
the morphology
all right least action
math
morphology
stephen
yeah i i don't know if we could unpack a
little bit more what dean was saying
there i'm i'm interested in
some of the implications of that um
work around looking at the math and
morphology
as it scales from these
what you might call smaller
scales than we can normally perceive
often what's going on with morphogenesis
is not
something we can be consciously aware of
a lot of the time however
who we are is built upon
morphogenesis
so i'm i'm very curious around
how some of these first principles can
be thought of as rolling out so when we
talk about lease action
has been one way of approaching it where
people often think about
um
energy
and efficiency of energy
processes as being the route that
everything will take
the more informational bayesian
inference
approaches and learning that
is implied by this
without
sort of distracting from the paper i'm
curious about people's thoughts about
what sort of
uh
implications that has for thinking about
these bottom-up
ways of knowing
okay blue
so i have
some questions going back even to before
least action in the paper
talking about generalized flow
and it's really interesting um just in
light of the paper that's coming up
in number 40
but but here um you know we see that
this is like a spatial like we're
talking about spatial motion here or
like the foundation for the way that
they model morphogenesis is
you know positions of particles through
space right like and time
and i just i just wonder um
like we have a time evolution
here and we're talking about motion in
space
but
could we do the reverse and talk about
like a space evolution in terms of
time like
it in terms of like can we invert space
and time
um
here so that's just it's something that
i was
curious about if it's
possible or mathematically illegal or
why am i even thinking like that i don't
know um
and another question that i had um
you guys were we're really talking about
um
you know the the in the generalized flow
we talked about the equations of motions
coordinates of motion
and the derivatives
uh and something that i saw in the paper
specifically at equation 15
that i've not seen before is p with a
dot and it was not defined in the paper
p with a dot but i'm assuming it's the
first derivative of p and i just thought
um that that was
interesting
so it's the probability density but is
it the derivative of the probability
density with respect to x with the tilde
or is it just p dot because x has a
tilde
anyway
that's my my question there
all right wow well we have a lot kind of
uh on
the table
i think the thing blue
appended with generalized flow is a good
entry point because this is sort of what
the
system's state evolution is and in
live stream number 26 with bayesian
mechanics we also talked about the
generalized coordinates of motion
with relationship with control
so
it's kind of like a thermometer
cybernetic model
if you only have the position of the
temperature there's certain strategies
that can be applied given that
modeling just simply the temperature
and then if you are modeling
progressively higher and higher levels
of how the system changes it's kind of
like a taylor series it equates to
basically a better depth of control
and then part of the hard part is that
because over the time course that action
is being planned for
even hypothetically
changes in
like the unknown consequences of one's
action complicate the estimation of
different policies
so this is just not like a total
perfect way to roll out the system and
understand how it's going to happen but
it gives like approximation terms to
higher and higher levels of the system
changing
and so that's the um
and all of the levels of analysis are
being linked to each other by being
derivatives of each other so then some
stationarity like is
capped out at some point so the
derivative becomes zero and then that's
like a heuristically
approximatable
um
depth of that model
so that's just like one note
of what is being estimated on so it's
like temperature and its higher order
components
in some
either analytical kind of
infinite generalized way
or just more practically with some
smaller realization
and then
the dot is like a derivative pretty sure
to blue like it's like a prime like
prime prime for double derivative two
dots for two derivatives
um
[Music]
and then morphogenesis is like position
of
particles
um
here it's like the cell
body or the cell nuclei
or the center of gravity of something
and then those are spatially moving so
that's the lowest level of this chain of
the integrator chain with the
generalized coordinates of motion
so that's how it's from a bayesian
mechanics
getting to
morphogenesis with just how particles
are moving in space
but instead of just modeling like their
x and their y it's like x and y and the
higher level
derivatives
so that's the developmental
motion of
particles
just to summarize that part before
the space and time okay any
thoughts on that because the generalized
flow is definitely where
whatever least action is is going to be
based in
um okay so then
let's just look at that
formalism
here is the derivatives okay anything on
this yeah yeah yeah yeah so if you're
gonna look at the at the formalism um
did you pull it up here yeah generalized
there you go um
so go ahead and then i'll i'll interject
yeah here's 2.2.1
x tilde is the total
blur of all the dots on top
so yeah go for blue
so just here the um
my question more is the noise and
fluctuation
term
um and is that just like brownian motion
or
i don't know so
yeah like what is the where is the omega
random fluctuation
like is it just
i don't know random in in terms of
browning motion or is there some other
random fluctuation positionally
like do things wiggle
definitely someone who knows more about
uh
stochastic processes and
i know several people listen who do
um could help with this
like in a math stream on
a little bit of the stochastic aspect
here
but i think at a first pass
um
there's situations where the
what is modeled as
noise
versus what is modeled as signal have
differential ratios
so there's times where like the
regression is very
the f even if the regression another
function is like very tight and then the
noise is modeled as low
versus
one where just the location of x is just
dominated by the noise term but
i'm sure it's way more
than that too
um
stephen or
dean
well i was just gonna
you know often when we see i'm just
thinking broadly in terms of the
modeling approaches and active inference
often
it brings in temperature as a way to
sort of bring in the kind of noise
fluctuations
into models whereas here
it's directly seen as a noise
fluctuation term
um
so i think that's uh
maybe it's again because we're going
down to even more first principles here
that it's getting down to stochastic
dynamics which isn't necessarily even
thought of as temperature but something
um
more more foundational
okay
um yeah blue
so temperature
um
is like yeah right like with increasing
temperature um like
random motion would increase so that
does um make sense to me
so another um
point out of this section or maybe if
anybody else has a point here
um going down into the next like set of
equations
unless anybody else yes
yeah just to summarize that it's kind of
like the temperature parameter is
understood sometimes to play this role
of
mediating the difference between the
particles
motion being driven by
some sort of directed
motion
um like change in position through time
not at stationarity of position which is
like kind of the observable in that
chain
that
directed motion
versus thermal slash brownian
and then um
[Music]
that might be kind of where these
statistical assumptions come into play
so it's like variance estimation but
temperature is just one kind of variance
with the move the motion
of particles
but and it has a it has a physical
interpretation in it and i mean it's not
an insignificant
piece i don't know
we could explore more where temperature
specifically comes into play but stephen
i think you're getting at the right
thing that this is not temperature bound
but it does relate to that sort of
situation okay blue
um so i don't know if you want to go
down to equations um 15 and 16 this is
probably where my next
question or comment is
do you have them in there or no oh copy
it in right now cool
go for it
so
it says
um
equation 15
uh
i think that's x tilde dot yes
p x tilde um it is a probability current
which i thought that that was cool
because i've never really heard of that
like term of probability current like
how
probability changes over time or or um
the probability density changes over
time like what is a probability current
like that was just it's an interesting i
don't know
um
like term that i hadn't heard before
and then in the second um equation 16
it says that um this is a partial
differential equation that describes the
time evolution of the probability
density under dissipative and
conservative forces so where the term on
the left is the dissipative forces and
the term on the right is the
conservative forces
and i thought like that that was
interesting especially relating back to
the dot zero video um
where you guys were talking about a
tensor and dean was talking about
tension and i think that there's is like
an interesting
tension here between like conserving and
dissipating and it just makes me like
wonder how um
how like
like is death when like the dissipative
like term is winning like is that like
what causes like a system or i mean i
know that the term you know winning or
term being greater doesn't cause a
system to die or when a system is
decomposing
if that can be represented here in terms
of these dissipative and conservative
forces um in the process of an organism
dying or ceasing to exist
okay sorry i have way more questions
than nice nice let's let's look at 15
and 16 a little bit so yes probability
current it's kind of in this dynamical
systems framing
it's being
bridged with
formalisms that are like more like a
current like a flow
on
a dynamical landscape
there's that sort of angle but then
there um
and maybe there's also more of a fluid
flow component blue
it's a timer
i was needed so like it's funny when i
look up a probability current like also
foreshadowing foreshadowing the dot zero
it says in quantum mechanics the
probability current sometimes called
probability flux is a mathematical
quantity describing the flow of
probability
um so so it's interesting that it's
related to quantum mechanics and in
terms of these like
instead of these classical physics um
things that we've kind of been
looking at or dealing with so far
um yeah so this
is
okay this might be a only a partial
element or for example hopefully one
that is useful so this is x tilde with a
dot so that's x tilde all the
coordinates of motion and then
x with a dot means derivative of so this
left parameter with a tilde and a dot is
how the generalized coordinates are
changing through time
so that's kind of what is being modeled
the data that are being whether they're
an observable or an unobserved estimated
state in a bayesian graph so whether
it's an o or an s
that plus it's all of its derivatives
and then that is being partitioned into
one big
complex function
f
modeling it
flow
and then
this noise omega tilde over both are
over tilde
so the these are both over like each of
these higher derivatives also have an
associated noise term
and then it says
yeah okay stephen
in some ways
there could be an analogy i'm not saying
it's the same but there's a there seems
to be a mirroring of the
enthalpic turn and entropic terms you
get in gibbs free energy where
one is where there's
this the energy is bound within
the molecules at play
and then the other term this
entropic term where it's kind of
dissipating so
um
then
it's it's another
because these things are
is translatable just like mass and
energy are translatable and they're
known to ultimately be conserved
um
they can only be
the overall
mass energy
of a system is always conserved but it
could be translated between
normally we don't think about that
because it only happens in nuclear
reactions but
if you're thinking informationally it's
still and this and i see they talk about
this idea of probability mass
so that there's almost uh
an ability to think about that
conservation of um
energy in a form which has mass which
has form
as opposed to when things have
dissipated as light
where it doesn't have mass anymore
okay blue
so i think where they're talking about
the conservation of probability
mass i think that they mean like the
conservation of the total
probability
there like so the probability mass
function right right like so i think
it's that um which which relates to like
the it's the conservation of mass but
it's also the conservation of
information
using that conservation of probability
like the probability of all of the
possible things happening has to add up
to 100
like that probability is never going to
change
um and so i think that that
is there
that it has to add up to one
like a fraction or a hundred percent
uh has the realist and
and instrumentalists
take
the realest take is something has to
happen
and then the instrumentalist take is
if we model it this way we're going to
be able to use statistics
but if it was like well the chance of
getting heads is 60 and the chance of
getting tails is 60
in this next flip
it would open up the space
in a different way
um it it's kind of outside the bounds of
the model you could have a model where
both happen
but still there's
it's a different thing you know can you
model things that can't happen in the
real world or
if it's not a good measuring stick for
statistics which is kind of like that
one
something must happen we have to model
something happening we have to model a
data set row being added otherwise what
is happening if it were like one
one every one every 1.2 rows
so
um
and then here yeah steven
in relation to the point you just made
i'm just curious whether if these
functions can be used in multiple
um particles
um in say for instance you have the
probe the idea is the probability of a
coin being flipped is 50 50 for instance
or a rigged coin could be 60 40 in one
way
however
the
probability if there's noise
on how rigged something is so for
instance you've got you've got a coin
and it's flipping between being rigged
60 40
50 50
40 30.
so there's kind of a there's a random
fluctuation in
that behavior which maybe contextually
contingent
that in itself wouldn't be in the one
equation but if you had multiple
particles
there they could start to behave not
just as one
predictable thing they themselves could
have the change in probability
approaches
thanks blue
so i i think like specifically as
related to here and i think that this is
derived like i'm not i don't like really
know um i don't really do these like
derivations it's definitely not my area
of expertise but i think
in in terms of the conservation of mass
like like we're not creating or
destroying matter
the conservation of the probability mass
it just says that all the particles if
you're looking at it doesn't matter if
it's one particle or a thousand
particles the particles are
somewhere
right like so the particles are not
nowhere like the particles are
somewhere so so it's that kind of
concert that's like the idea that you
know all the probability has to add up
to one like there is 100 chance that you
will find the particle of interest
somewhere i mean
you write
okay
um
[Music]
yeah blue good section to uh pull out
important some important bridge
equations
so we have the signal to noise now when
the signal that we're modeling
with the instrumentalist take we're
modeling how much the cow weighs
defined as
the one that
comes to walk over to me when i call for
it or something like that
that could be dominated by
different functions
or could be driven by different noise
on different time skills
so the signal
sort of directed motion component or
modelable component
of
the motion through time is the purple
and here is like some
flow with the upside down triangle
that we talked a little bit about in dot
zero but would of course be good to hear
from someone who knows more about this
flow
um
operator
object
um
signal
is like the movement on a probability
distribution
on those states changing
and then
the noise
is
the dissipative
component
stephen
it appears as well that by
breaking it into dissipative and
conservative
components it's um
it's serving a similar
role to separating into complexity and
accuracy
it's given a way to
um
break apart
for dissipation um
where the um
because you're not actually talking
about a final target
but more like you
things just doing what they do in some
ways and having a very
kind of physics
fundamental process
i think that's proven to be useful
because it's also again
something which can be translated into
different
different types of
math different types of physics
okay so let's connect it to the
morphogenesis so what do they do in the
paper they're modeling the motion of
cells so why does it matter this whole
discussion that we're having
about how to get from the motion of
generalized coordinates if you're the
modeler you get to define that and get
to set the parameter between this
if you're the
experimentalist then you're inferring
this kind of like a regression like if
this was a regression term and a noise
term on the regression
that and then there's some function that
helps you
fit a certain solution
to the one linear regression that fits
it best
so it's like kind of in that same
genre here
so if we take the realist take
um
on that it's like how the actual system
is defined as or inferred to be as from
experimental data
and then flowing the probability
density on that of our inference on that
whether we're getting that from the data
or whether we're
defining that system formally
so
that modeling
we get help from the
authors or someone else like
it engages some new
future
it's like a bridge to some other set of
equations so
that's where it would be good to learn
more like what is actually enabled here
but it enables a new
vista
that separates that that enables this
separation
so we can talk about instead of this
like potentially extremely open-ended
and non-linear change on the system
can be bounded within a statistical
inference
zero to one
inference framework
that
is more amenable to certain kinds of
analysis
so
that would help
model cell location and
all of that
but i think there's still a lot more to
learn there and
unpack okay dean yes
so i want to just sort of step back for
a second here because i want to go
we started out
talking about someone what are the
implications for least action
so the act part and then we
sort of stepped into the idea of what
what came before the action well it was
these flow states and i kind of want to
go back to the action part in this in
the
under that section 222 the second
paragraph says that
the least action principle can predict
the emergence of forms so what daniel
was mentioning there that sort of the
morphogenesis
in terms of the flow or paths of least
action in biological systems for example
in colonies
ants find the paths of least action to
harvest food and bring it to the colony
the example considers their paths as
flow channels or trajectories finding
the least average
action for each instance of foraging
given available resources so this gets
me thinking
about what do we mean by
least action as opposed to say most
action and
that that that
general way the general way
that things tend to follow like if you
thought of an
analogy of
of uh maybe 18 19th century war where
armies would line up facing one another
uh
parallel to one another
this is speaking more like a flow state
more like you find in nature where the
the molecules we talked about here are
sort of flowing and following down the
side of a bowl to the least potential
energy
and so
now my question is okay so why does
nature
tend to
flow with the advantage of least
action whereas people with
instruments
don't necessarily
flow or follow one another unless
they're mirroring
some other form or some other shape
so
it's interesting to me because i think
by nature we are quite adaptable
but when we start making
uh non-living things as instruments to
necessarily take the nature away the
life away where maybe not as quite as
adaptable so
i'm trying to bring it i'm trying to
step back and
now pull us back into this idea of so
what advantage is there
in this physics
view of least action there must be
something advantageous there in nature
so what is it i'm not the geneticist so
i don't know what this what the signal
milieu is
that
makes that so so i want to tap your
guys's
and gals's
expertise on this because i don't have
it
all right thanks dean stephen
so following on what dean's saying there
i think with um
in
the traditional sense we tend to take
what we call equilibrium dynamic
approaches so for instance the arm we
the armies are lined up like dean said
then there's a battle
and then there's the final state so we
talk about the initial conditions which
is equilibrium everyone lined up and the
final state
and then the bit in the middle
we sort of talk into our shirt or our
shoulder or whatever
cough a few times and somehow it
happened
and
in some ways with the biological
approach it's like it's in that
because all that bit in the middle is
where the flow is happening so
essentially speaking
and biology doesn't have those
initial conditions in the sort of
traditional sense of pure equilibrium
it's always in this non-equilibrium
or at least a large component is in a
non-equilibrium state so this is an
interesting
thing as it's flowing down towards
the least energy
it never reaches it so we might you know
i think that's uh it always so for
instance in in the chemical reactions
you you set you you take your pure
reactants
you mix them together
you stir it up you do the reaction and
then once you've got your product which
could be a precipitate for instance
which you know it could be a ton of the
precipitate it then gets filtered it
gets washed it gets dried
and it gets measured for how pure it is
and now it's in this kind of stable
product form you know
um so i think yes
this this this question about
what does it mean to flow
[Music]
um is really important
thanks steven all right dean
well what this what this flowing and
following thing
kinda says is that
the the desire line or the or the
termite mound the result
is of signaling
which
which is
i don't know if that's collective
signaling i i don't know if it's the
stigma she part of it like i i don't
know
why nature sees the advantage
in the following
but there has to be something there why
why
why is that advantageous why is that
more adaptable
versus the alternative
okay thanks stephen
well i suppose one way of looking at
that is it's the only
cause i mean if we're going to take a
realist route uh recognizing that it
maybe it's the only plausible route on
the table
um
we we they don't get to
you know
forge teeth in a kiln or
you know in a way that's partly why all
chemicals that are available in nature
have to be within
certain plausible
um temperature scales and pressure
scales
that that can yield those react those
products at
so
i mean that kind of doesn't answer the
question exactly because i know that's
kind of a bit of a
but it's part of it's what's available i
think
in terms of um biological plausibility
um and i suppose in some ways humans we
we we've adapted a cognition to try and
move outside that
okay yeah dean
now one last thing on this and that is
that
following implies that there's also
something leading there always has to be
something taking that
that initiative for others to
fall in line behind
so
shifting that and making leadership
something that's more lateral
so sort of going forward
together as opposed to
who do who do we decide to
to
follow behind that's an interesting
thing in terms of sort of assessing out
how this least action principles things
turns into things that we actually
see phenomenal phenomenologically so
again we're going to get into the what
what the final form takes i just think
that when we were
sort of treating this in the point zero
this was kind of piv a pivotal moment
because it went from what are all the
things that have to be in place for
formation to occur
to now let's let's look at what the what
the form now
results as and as as i said in here in
that one paragraph it said
um
well the previous paragraph says physics
offers a useful formalism to understand
at a quantitative level the ability of
biological systems to work towards
so now we're we're basically now
moving to something that is that is
adaptable
so i think like i said i don't want to
over
over talk this one point but i think
it's an interesting part in terms
especially when we get into the the
discussion at the end
around why
what what some of the assumptions were
in yada yada
okay
thanks yeah stephen
this work towards um idea i mean that
can be
thought of in a as a modeling and a life
realist problem like how how does that
work towards
uh and
in some ways
accuracy and complexity
can
be used once we
if we're at the level of assuming that
we are actively inferring to stay alive
but
prior to that
something like
conservation and dissipation
or conserved
are
a bit more foundational okay because
if
by
conserving or working within this
conserving dissipating noise
dynamic
at the levels which are below what we
are consciously aware of however which
all our cognition is effectively built
upon somewhere
we
we're able to
potentially
give that towards us
without necessarily having set a goal
and it could be and i think that's
um
that might be an interesting see how
that rubs out in the real
real world
of of active influence labs and papers
and stuff
um
yeah
cool
yeah a lot you link there stephen just
now like accuracy complexity
and then okay
we'll leave it for a future
day and
work and who knows how many of these are
just concordances versus total logical
but
accuracy within a model
is like
pragmatic aims within a model with the
imperative to prefer to fit as much data
as possible
and then it's like
um conservative
um
using the reward structure that worked
at one time step
using that generative model moving
forward versus changing it
any sort of dispersion around the
parameters as
evidenced at the lowest level of the
chain the position of the particles
or the actual parameter that's being
modeled like the actual
image that's being percepted on
versus these higher generative models
which don't realize like at the kind
of um you know tip of a javelin so to
speak
so then the signal and noise is also
like
conservation and dissipation
with
respect to the model and then that is
coming all the way back to morphology
with like the position in stasis versus
vibration of the particle from thermal
so it's like a lot that gets
linked here but
where's least action in all of this
like
yeah blue
so just to read a quote
from the paper
it says
since
self-organizing open systems are not
conservative
their structured flow is
quintessentially dissipated dissipative
and so and and that's like you know down
it's in the third paragraph in the least
action principle section
so it just that goes back to what i was
saying um earlier
like
does that equate to death like when the
system
totally dissipates like it's ultimately
dissipative so you know we stay in this
like nest for a little while and then
we dissipate right like is that can can
it be modeled like these processes using
these equations i find that super
interesting
yeah
um thanks steven
this this um this idea of the least
action i think the timing of what blue
was saying there as well is um
it's least action maybe we should say
dynamical least action as opposed to
least action which we normally think of
i.e
well like i was saying reactants
products
what was what's the what's you know
what's the route to get from a to b
or the army lined up to
final space
um normally we are taking
starting conditions ending conditions
um or
you know where i am now what's my goal
what's the least to get there but those
two things are defined in some ways
they're they're definable so i think
it's a good now
all the bit in between
is um
trying to go to least action
um
in some way um using that kind of in in
the space of chaos i suppose if we're
going to take
the kind of complexity approach in human
systems
um
it's in a chaotic state where you're
trying to at some time um make sense of
how to act
but however
you know in some ways there's only
chaos moving into complexity
which is available
at some biological
systems theoretically maybe not the idea
of complicated and
kind of simple
sort of reproductive
sort of
steady
like equilibrium state systems like
mechanical systems aren't necessarily
available although you could argue that
maybe certain properties of our
morphology like our
um
our bone structure and that so gives
something which is approximate to that
um
once we know how to move our arm we have
a relatively simple
thing that we can now
bring into our regime of attention but
uh yeah i wonder what people think of
dynamical least action is is somehow
what's going on here
yeah thanks steven just
here's one
take on that it's a good
idea question i hope this is accurate
too because
i think we're all
learning here but this is definitely a
really
challenging area in some ways to
approach especially
given our realistically limited
familiarity
so
again it'd be awesome for people who
have more familiarity with these
equations to
join us like either in preparation or
even just joining us on these streams so
that we can actually
learn and connect to these other areas
somebody who sees this formalism like
every day just like we might see some
other one
okay
but
stephen brought up is this a dynamical
leased auction okay so first kind of
a hopefully non-contentious point that
we're analyzing what we model we can
only ask the computer to calculate the
numbers that we ask it to model and add
we can't expect something that goes
truly beyond that not to say that the
models can't have surprising outputs or
interactions etc but we can't have it go
beyond what we specify
and
the model
is
over x tilde
which is the generalized coordinates of
motion which is the position
and all of the higher derivatives the
whole
integrator chain
position in all higher order moments of
the statistical distribution they're
called moments like the first second
third moment of the derivatives of the
statistical distribution
and these are basically
terms of approximation of motion
that allow a high order like a taylor
series approximation or a volterra
series approximation
to
allow snapshot modeling
with real-time flow
action cognition perception it's the
flow over
as
gets explored
the
blanket
states this is like the flow over s a
and i
states actions and um internal states
so like this is
enabling a flow description of
markov blanket states
and their
perception cognition action their flow
overstates their change their time
including higher order moments of time
so that it is a dynamical systems model
but still there has to be a snapshot
like a time series model of a stock
price
it has a value at
whatever time resolution or continuous
or discrete
it's being time series modeled at
so it's kind of the relationship between
snapshot modeling and capturing higher
order trends
and this is a certain way to think about
that
in the direction that they're going to
take it
towards the markov blanket partitioning
and bridging it to everything that that
affords okay
um dean and then stephen
this is really important because i think
it i want to tease something that maybe
we can look at right right here but only
in the 0.2 so
between the
us doing the live stream zero
and today
there was a report about the rate at
which
climate i think was the u.n report the
rate at which climate change is
happening so rapidly that
as as
the people who are
sort of
in that highly
changing flow state aren't able to
necessarily going to be able to adapt
to the rate of change and so i wonder if
some of what this paper speaks to
might help us understand
why
the authors of that report
are indicating to us that the
the environment in which we we are
existing in is going to change so
quickly
that as cells within that larger
structure
our form is not going to be able to
adapt quickly enough
to the way that the
external system is is changing so i want
to save that for the point too but i
think this least action principle part
would be a good entry point into some of
these bigger questions going forward so
i just want to park that but i think it
matters
yeah just to give one
note on that
the rate of change and how it changes
those are kind of natural language
descriptions of
derivatives of how things are changing
might be a simple
claim to some but that's really
important to keep in mind so how things
are changing
and then that's always going to be
unknown
to some degree
so
how things change and so on this is the
generalized coordinates of motion
and so it is about modeling rates of
change and predictability of systems um
that i've raised to change and
okay yes
stephen
with this you we mentioned there about
your action perception cognition and in
some ways the cognition is
organization on
the generative model and the genitive
model
is
an action
policy model okay so we've got this
recognition coming in but it's drive by
this action and of course one challenge
you've got in the climate change
scenario is um
really what you think is
one thing but being able to act and
being
i mean the danger is we hit a point
where no matter how much we know is
beyond the ability to act
in our
capabilities and uh capacities as a as a
as a species um
the
so this this while i think the word
cognition is useful it may be useful to
be careful just that
the inference process is more general
because it can be it can be a process
which is like say happening beyond
thought
um so
thought is a
is is another action
almost giving a higher order
understanding on the generative motion
product generative model for an action
in active influence
and of course a lot of
what's going on underneath is is beyond
our perception
literally um way beyond so
uh that that that can be interesting or
useful to
strip out
nice
yeah blue thanks
so just to kind of go back to dynamical
least action i do think that that's what
they're referring to
at the very end of the section the
authors say
from our perspective the key observation
here is that any dissipative random
dynamical system can be formulated as
gradient flow
on the log likelihood of its states this
is reflected in our solution to the
focker planck equation in 17
which means the action is the time or
path integral of the marginal likelihood
or self-information
for any system or model m
so this is really the key thing this
means the least action integral over the
lagrangian turns into an integration
over the self-information of states
which is known as entropy in information
theory in short the principle of least
action manifests as a principle of least
entropy for systems that possess a
random dynamical attractor and thereby
obtain non-equilibrium steady state
thanks a lot blue great
um point
good day franz
hi hi sorry that i'm late and uh i
only have a half an hour too i'm in the
middle of fighting preschool so daycare
is a whole mess right now i do apologize
i do want to take this time
it's a little bit of a mess next week
should be better i think we found school
so hopefully next time here we go
easy
cool
unexpected but preferred you know how
will we model that
um but thanks a lot for joining this is
really cool
so we were just describing
some of the formalisms but
where would you like to begin it'd be
awesome to hear like any
just introduction and context on the
paper and then we kind of jumped in at
least action
and would love to hear your take on that
sure
um all right slow interactions i guess
um i'll decide myself so um i i work in
mclean's lab and tufts and doing a phd
in biology
and this is
the whole kind of active inference um
part of my work is came actually before
my entire phd so i joined mike's lab
because i wanted to
really learn what kind of information
and physics do in a biology context i
didn't i didn't want to study the whole
level of
you know i mean i'm still doing as a
technique but i didn't want to have the
focus on protein interaction and you
know genetic information um where you
measure all these things so i was based
on something a bit more broader than
that
and so when i reached out to him like
and once i got some accepted he um i was
like you know i have some months to kill
can you send me somewhere or do
something cool and then he sent me to
carl frist and that's when that's the
first time i heard the term active
inference so i spent about four months
in carl's lab
um and then basically started working on
on on the
i think half the work in the paper i was
actually done in those those couple
months and when i was in carl's lab
so the the overall goal of the paper and
of that part of my work is to see if we
look at morphogenesis and
similar biological processes can we look
at something where you have a very kind
of um kind of baseline stem cell like
behavior where you have cells that kind
of do like a morphogenesis basically i
don't know how much you're familiar with
the whole biology aspect of this paper
but essentially it's the ideas you model
cells that are uninformed they have some
kind of you know genetic code something
that encodes their their their structure
the
the basically you have the genetic
process already ingrained in the
genitive model into the into the cells
but they're completely by their stem
cell like they don't have actually yet
achieved their final form um and they're
just like in the simulation and biology
right they're starting off with very
few asymmetries this i think there's a
famous
who said that but
uh some physicians that once said most
of physics is basically just uh
symmetries that's symmetry everywhere
and that's exactly kind of um
how most biologies things but i'll just
think of of morphogenesis there's some
asymmetry in in the beginning
in the egg where some there's some some
different information
some gradient of something some
localization of certain agents and then
from that on basically everything else
just follows through
but it's it's it's hard to believe
that's the whole side of the story
because there's just so much complexity
and so many cells doing at the same time
so
if there isn't any capability for them
to adapt to signals and environment and
to learn from each other it's hard to
believe that the time frame they're
given they can really um you know
achieve the complex morphogenesis
outcomes that we know
um do exist so coming to this paper
basically this model is actually already
um like the the father or mother of this
paper was already done before i even
heard of this topic that that was the
knowing once place so the model
structure itself was already done like i
think called it most if not all of it
and mike just basically
was on the paper and giovanni as well
they basically gave him some input on on
on what
what the background of biology would
look like
and so they already figured out
basically let's do a simplistic model
eight cells there's more as far as i
know from carl and it's like myself in
my simulations many practical concerns
don't mind too complex
if you have too many cells at once um
then then you're gonna run into problems
in the beginning something i actually
added on to the model um even the
baseline model was that damping
parameter um which i talked later on in
the results which might often like it's
not a key part but i find it very
interesting because that's one of the
requirements for active infants um for
for fear and energymization variation of
the energy minimization there's a smooth
landscape and when you have all these
cells initially clustered together and
they're trying to infer their place and
they all kind of have some random
randomly initialized prior beliefs they
don't know where to go from there and if
you
right if you have already high precision
in there and the sensory apparatus
initially they have a really hard time
they still end up mostly fine and
getting later but they jump all over the
place and you can imagine that'd be very
bad for an anabolic scenario if every
cell immediately jumps to the first
queue they have we actually think now in
the mclean labs that um a lot of cancer
initiation happens a little bit like
that where positions are as i said too
high um there's a paper coming out soon
by my colleague of mine that talks a bit
more about that argument
but so basically from
um we had the target mythology already
always encoded that and you saw what you
see in the in the baseline control
experiments was already done
what i was interested in is basically
again coming back to my my question and
my approach to this from the biology
side of you
is how can we use the asp of information
flow and specifically active inference
to manipulate and base better control of
genesis outcomes and control biology so
the the two main results in that in that
paper
are looking at if you instead of you
know stuff like a normal biology
experiment where you basically interrupt
one part of the machinery
um and then see how everything reacts
you actually control the process
information processing itself
so one was basically if you put in a
an asymmetry and the response of the
cells to their
to the signaling
um ligands they get the signaling
concentrations in the environment
how can you basically completely remodel
the entire morphogenesis outcome
even though you actually left the entire
code itself that's always one thing i
tried to stress in that paper the target
methodology and all the simulations is
exactly the same none of them they
basically said exact coding
um of what where they're supposed to be
but how the process information has been
changed
um so the first figure is that where you
have those two head and two tails um and
if i did the details in the in that or
if i just did it myself and then publish
it i think it's in there as well
um then
that's basically something that we also
see in the lab i think that was
mentioned as well that that's something
that that might have lab has done with
an area where they basically induce
those two head types right that's
something that's really weird to
biologists to and again in in the type
of
manipulations that we're doing all that
happened in this lab they didn't
manipulate the genetic and the natural
code again the the dna from those panera
that specifically was exactly the same
but somehow they perturbed the actual
bioelectric network
um itself so basically on the state
space essentially so that kind of like
where this inspiration came from
and then the second part where we the
the malformation or i also talk about
cancer information and of course it's
it's
completely called cancer because we
didn't put proliferation in this in this
um simulation so that's it's the
initiation stage but it's the idea is
that again under something that we
talked about also in the lab and recall
many emails afterwards and it kind of
also goes back to this whole idea with
um
how how different psychiatric orders
work in the brain where you have some of
these inference processes being
disrupted and then lead to large scale
outcomes but they kind of start
somewhere the idea was here is that if
we disrupt only the um the information
flow from one cell to the other cells
and the other cells to that one cell
then what would what would that cell do
so basically just completely reduced its
um
sensitivity to the environment
um and then saw it happen and what
happened was that this one cell
basically kind of like
it didn't it didn't move a whole lot it
got it inferred the wrong kind of cell
type
um and it was completely out of place
right so that's always baton biology if
a cell is doing something that's not
supposed to in a place where it's not
supposed to be um and what i thought was
interesting afterwards well okay so how
can we rescue that and again like right
i'm not trying to rescue it in a
traditional cancer therapy idea where
you bombard the cell or just kill it how
can you actually have the system remodel
itself so that the idea was to
increase the um so the sensitivity was
still disrupted from that one cell but
then the flow like how much concentrate
how much the other cells reacted to it
so basically we manipulated how the
information flow from the other cells to
that cells was flowing and increased
that
so and then what was interesting is that
the kind of they were just kind of like
going more closely into an interaction
we just seen this time lapse figure
um and then eventually they reshape so
even though the cells like normally if
you run this it's a deterministic
simulation right it's like um it's
random it's always the same random seed
so you run the simulation and you want
again it'll be awesome outcome so you
can kind of know which cells go where
even though you know no cell starts off
with like knowing i'm supposed to be in
that cell that's not how it happens but
because we run the simulation with a
fixed and randomized seed we always know
which cell ends up going where and and
then in that cancer simulation that was
not the same anymore so actually even
though at the end after that rescue
experiment they ended up with a
perfectly normal shape and then followed
in the mythology at the end it wasn't
what normally was supposed to happen
right the cells that normally have gone
to their fixed positions didn't all do
that so there was some reconfiguration
which is something that that's that's an
ideal strategy that you would like right
something that you exploit the system's
interaction itself to then rescue it and
overall target more you want to work on
the the phenotype but you want to work
on what's actually wrong you don't care
exactly what cell does and and is
implemented there's a lot of cool
science little tangential but that's
really cool work but eve marta that
works on neuronal networks and lobsters
where they see that this works in life
vegas it's a simple enough system to
work only but what they're seeing is
there's actually a multitude of
implemented implementations that the new
neural neural network can can use and do
use individuals these entirely different
parameters with like two to four full
differences in iron challenge
concentrations to achieve the same end
result and it's actually the the
response to resilience to stress to
perturbations in the environment is that
in the details but in the end the actual
homeostatic aspect of it is kept the
same right the goal of having something
um end up the same
stephen would like to speak uh go go
ahead
oh hi thanks yeah i was just gonna
one question
is
the idea of flow in a way more flow is
better
even though that
um so unlike i say a generative model
where you maybe don't want too much
complexity
you can have a lot of flow but as long
as that flows not noise um
it just is able to inform so that's the
first part and the second part is are
you saying it's
with this flow it's about finding
where the choice point is or whether the
threshold is to say
okay that's now
going to decide that that's going to
create a morphological
target
as opposed to it just being a gradual
gradient descent on energy
it it is more aggression aspect so the
it is i would say it's it's not ideal to
think about decision points even though
in the end it doesn't happen it's
something that we're just we're used to
in our level of speech
but on the level of of outside online
cells that is very much gradual process
right at this basically you have all
these different probabilities which are
probabilities of being one cell in the
other and the simulation
and uh the idea of increasing
information flow or increased
sensitivity with our aspect your
modeling and manipulating or precision
as well
is that you are trying to get
the vibration for energy to be minimized
but also specifically to converge on a
system where those probabilities
actually end up somewhere meaningful
right where if you don't want to be in a
state where they're constantly
fluctuating constantly randomized either
you mentioned noise that's one aspect
you want to avoid you also want to avoid
that they basically um
do this and like that
that's where you write the decision
point right like that the cell is
basically going towards one state and
then there was a wrong one and then you
increase the information flow of the
other cells and the cancer rescue from
um stimulation
to bring it away from that but you're
not
you first of all not actually working on
like you know identifying that point and
then you're fixing that you're basically
just just uh realizing that the
the simulation overall basically you
basically look at the the probability
changes over time so how are they
updating and how fast are they updating
and then of course in the end what are
they updating towards and that gives you
a cue
if you think from experimental point of
view or even like experimental
assimilation or point of view then that
tells you okay so um if if that happened
too fast if there was
malformation happening too fast then you
probably want to act and you want to
increase sensitivity or something um
early on but you don't do it at one time
you just set the parameters for the
whole simulations but it tells you
basically the strength that the
sensitivity is with respect to how early
and how strongly that misinformation is
happening does that answer your question
somewhere
yeah i think that does one i suppose one
question just on that is
is it
is there like an optimum level in terms
of this flow
um i it peaks or is it like the more
flow you can get the better it's just
literally
a limit on
how much information flow is possible
um
well the short answer is that the boring
answer is that always will depend on the
context i would say um there is no i i
don't think you can say you know more
like the broad statement like more
information feels always better
doesn't make sense i think you already
gave the answer to that why that is
right because you in the end it will end
up too much noise based on the system so
that answer has to be a respect of how
much information actually is being can
be processed what is the time scale of
the sensory parameters some my
experimental work works a lot on um i'm
basically having different uh
variation of input signals to my model
system which is actually an algae i'll
get to that but long story short i
actually had once got the question that
where i was at these randomized signals
and that was defeating it um and then
someone asked like well you actually
this is actually taking more information
because you're having and i was like
well and that like white noise
technically carries more right more
variation but it's not informative right
so that's
more information flow by itself is not
better more informative information flow
the informative part being is actually
does it how quick does it change over
time so there's a lot of important
aspect other directors there and with
respect to also the sensory precision
and you know the timings there's certain
time scales involved in like how center
space how fast
sensory states lead to updates of
internal states
all these things together make up
basically how fast an agent can react
and uh how much information can process
and that's
the optimal level will be dependent on
that essentially
okay awesome dean or blue before we have
anyone go again
so i have a question um can you flip to
figure four daniel please yep um
just so you had mentioned earlier on hi
by the way it's nice to see you i'm
really glad
we i'm glad you couldn't make it
it's a pleasant surprise um but here in
figure four you mentioned that you
didn't
model proliferation in this model but
it seems to me that there's like more
like it looks proliferative here so is
it just like a very dense cluster at the
first time step or do you duplicate it
every time step or like how
how did you end up with so many more um
like
beads or or whatever you know agents uh
cells at the end than at the beginning
that there might be an optical um so
a communication problem on my part so
the the the
the actual cells are eight in each of
those images all of them
but what you're seeing is the trace of
it right so only the ones that have like
the the the strongly colored dot and
then like the little star around it at
the end right if you look at the last
frames on there those are actually the
the cells and what you see in the back
is basically like time lapse kind of
like
snip snip snip shots they're not
actually cells in there
uh it would be actually interesting i
know you even thought of that that would
actually be a fairly simple uh
introduction that each of those point
steps you just make that and you sell
that'll be pretty cool actually um i i
know i i think basically carl
i know and one of us when he initially
published that i think he had way at the
end of the simulations he basically just
added some new cells but he never went
further with that and i think it's the
same problem that i mentioned that when
you have it initially and like in the
first time frame at t equals one
that if you have to make cells close
together it's um you have to kind of set
the sense the precision lower because
otherwise they're too close together i
mean it works somewhat but it's very
susceptible to perturbation at that
stage
so in order if you basically want to
reintroduce perforation either like you
said or like like you gave me the idea
to do in between what you do at the end
you would have to have more which of
course what cells do right if you have
new transformation that are not going to
be the same kind of sense of rest that
than a mature or a form cell is
um but that was basically i think just
for the simulation what was making a
little bit complicated but um
it is i'm not right now actively working
on that simulation anymore if i did
um that would be great yeah maybe i'll
come back to that
no that would be way cool and if it
needs to be like less sensitive at the
beginning like you just double the urge
or yeah you just double the sensitivity
at each um time step and then that way
like you know you would get that
enhanced sensitivity over time and it's
also very interesting from the point of
view of fractals and there's something
really cool right right now all stuff
but i recently read that wolfram the guy
behind often alpha
he's like signing this whole new physics
approach where they basically just have
simple set of rules and then they just
use fractal kind of multiplications and
then each each time that that goes on
and they create all these kind of physic
laws
um which i haven't yet gotten deep into
i can't really say anything about how
good and useful that is but
the fact that we all know is a very kind
of informative
mechanism that's used in biology
extensively
um and that's something you could use
here as well where basically each step
where you introduce a new cell you kind
of just have the same rule set with the
initial and you run like a
small simulation in that simulation
essentially and with the same simple set
of rules you could probably make up a
whole much more complex so it probably
looked nothing like this i i wouldn't
expect this to then afterwards still
have like the same shape but
cool stuff cool ideas about the top
just kind of unpack that because it's a
great suggestion and thanks for kind of
giving your take on two friends it's
really cool to hear like when the cells
divide you may need a first symmetry
breaker to introduce a symmetry break
you get some gradient it can be gravity
it could be a nutrient gradient it can
be the entry point of the sperm that
triggers a calcium wave but it's like
asymmetries can give rise to asymmetries
and then interacting you get two
morphogens and then now it's high high
and low low and then the alternations
influence gene regulation and that's
like very complex but um
adjacency effects are really important
and that's how we get the
self-organization like of the insect eye
or of tissues because they don't have to
do what this challenge is which is sort
of like getting formation spaced out
this is like the bird flock morphology
which is also so cool because it does
apply to other systems too
which i'm sure we'll be exploring more
but like
bodies fill out into a morphology not
just
dissolve this is yeah cool though i mean
of course we really
learned a lot let's return to least
action just and feel free just to leave
any time you'd like but on least action
where does it come into play
or what is it doing here
yes so it's
that was more of a background um section
so um
georgie gorgiev who is also on on that
paper is also my um
excellent bertie supervisor
um we kind of talked to him because
this is not nothing that i did and there
was like novel um i didn't like
it was not the way we framed it but i
didn't make it i didn't make new map for
that but the idea was that is that what
what yogi um who's doing all these
action principles you know the classical
action principles applied to biology
questions and he was like well you know
it's really
um i think you're missing like a
communication um
aspect of this where you're like you're
not going to be committing clearly how
this fits into these action principles
um and you're not going clearly of of
what
like where diverge essentially and um
car actually did by a people on to
whether he sprinkles in there but i want
to make this more explicit essentially
that that the variation pure aviation
principle is at least action principles
by definition essentially but what i was
trying to show here is um is simply kind
of like the the whole idea of this paper
from from background was that we could
anyone could start from this that has
more of a physics background and then
can work themselves to
through active inference to biology and
it's not that something that's
physically very familiar with white and
and the idea is actually where does this
um what is the interesting take on it
from the from the from the variational
free energy
and that's what um i think in the so you
start this general definition what is an
extrema
and then you kind of see later on that
the the whole definition of the
um
of the global clever diversion of
innovation of energy very much
corresponds to that and it's also
um just interesting to see basically
where where that takes from so that
that's not that answers your question
that's basically that the point of that
was more
not not that least action that i used
that particular equation i didn't use
the classical uh the typical equations
that carl uses for his variation for
energy there's more motivation and i
hope that goes to show essentially where
this all flows from like how how do you
get from
from you know from from from from the
opponent function in the beginning for
stability how or lagrangian function how
do you get from that to a variational
peer energy to really make that
um kind of integration into physics
tighter which i know i failed at because
there were the comments to that paper
that were published with it and if you
read that one two of them were like
you still don't see how the integration
is doing then my comment to that was
then i think i called that that mini
paper response paper like a cheaper
integration to physics so i know i
didn't succeed in that i apologize but
that was the goal
okay awesome
dean
would you like to go anywhere ask
anything
yeah i i don't even know no i'm just
gonna sit back and then
because
well well for me
you've taken a whole bunch of stuff
around what a form
might turn into
based on what signals it's
capable of
acting on is that
is that
a gross besides being a crossover
simplification can we start there does
that make sense
yeah so like
yes yes that makes sense basically what
what
i always like like talking about models
like what you put in what you get out
right so what we put into the model is
it's an encoding of signaling responses
which is like a classical like if you
see signaling a b but not much of c and
d
then you think your cell type
a whatever that means head type and then
you adjust your own signaling expression
so each cell basically has four
signaling molecules um that they can
exchange they can express they can sense
and based on different combinations of
those they think they're one or the
other
um and and that is semi-place encoded um
so they have basically from that map
that's what the type of morphology is is
meaning so what we put in basically is
is uh is that encoding the genetic model
um genetic process how they update that
the the particular diffusion constants
all that stuff that basically holds
information and spreads to each other
and then what we get out essentially is
is what kind of shapes like you said can
can emerge from that um
of course initially right the initial
model was basically you're not
interested in how many shapes because
you're interested can do the shape that
you put into it so the purpose of this
paper was is keeping that same target
the same kind of like i i um each cell
has these options that it can be based
on where it's sensing and then it's on
secreting but keeping with that can you
get different shapes
just by messing up the way that the
information flows in outside of the cell
and it's being processed around the
things that's again
that the inspiration from that comes
from the lab that i'm working on where
we do a lot of this where we don't don't
actually mess up the genetic genetic
coding so we don't mess up the genetic
model in inactive inference terms but we
mess up how how basically the the state
space looks like how information at each
point in time times updated and that's
that's the idea of this
what does it look like to engineer or
design a different target morphology
how did you fit
the bayesian model
or fit the
flow descriptor whatever it was in its
representation towards the represent
towards the um anatomy that's described
in figure three
yes so um
the the the the outcomes that we get
like the experimental outcomes here we
didn't like design the
fault like i said we keep those the same
we just basically had some intuition
that some of them found to be true of
how we could change it based on just the
asymmetry that we put in an information
flow
um how would we design this one um
mainly so this is an active level and
again this model itself is not that
that's already called this before i
joined it so that's not i didn't didn't
do as new but how do you approach this
so basically the idea is um this is the
idea of is fairly biological the idea is
that you have
chilling encodings where certain
transcription factors basically right
will
based on whatever you sense will then
basically activate gene expression in
the cells that were then allowed to
differentiate so cells most of
morphogenesis essentially starts off
from
um
from something i mentioned initially you
have some asymmetry in in signaling that
there's this thought that basically even
when you already have the
the the unfairlist egg in an animal
system
there's some asymmetry word that's being
stored actively by by the whole organism
of the mother essentially and based on
that asymmetry then you have gradient of
already of difference and then so
basically some cells will say will sense
more of signaling type a and lesser b
and then from that they will make they
will be um so certain things will be
expressed that will then um change the
sulfate to a
sub-sulfate and that and then you have
more sulfates and the same thing happens
there you have now more symmetry but
starting off in the same one so you
again will have cells that will sense
more and less of some signaling
thickness signaling ligands that will
basically then turn out to
be incorporated through transcription
factors
differential genetic expression
um to differentiation
so
what this is essentially what this is
doing right you're you're encoding what
what the codes here are essentially
those different
uh relationships between transcription
between signaling receptors
transcription factors downstream two
genetic code where then basically we
don't do proliferation again but there's
the the first step type there's
basically one snippet of type mythology
one aspect we have at that point in in
this hypothetical morphogenesis
experiments you have
four different signaling type signaling
cell type four different signaling
ligands um that that are being that
being expressed that can be expressed by
the cells and based on where you are in
the cluster you will see more or less of
it and based on that information you
will then yourself this cell start to
express more or less of because you
basically start differentiating
um so then we'll start expressing more
and less of that at some point of that
you reach certain threshold where they
actually will fully have undergone the
differentiation process and have a new
sulfate and that's what these different
um head tail and stuff so of course like
you know there's no
animal system dyno off that has a you
know eight cells and uh four cell types
and makes a whole body that would be
pretty crazy although there are some
interesting um there's some small
ornaments and systems where there are
um the these um the c elegans these are
one example where they have a a complete
map from from from cell to cell from
basically a gene so they know exactly
which cell base it turns out um to be
what cell the ends they can go from the
embryo and they can tell exactly this
cell is going to be at that at the end
of time
this is the minority of examples most uh
assembled most modal origins i know a
lot more messier than that and that's
what this um trying to basically answer
given that you have a lot of messi that
but cells can be different things
and then if perturbations happen like
they happen all the time in environment
and often we do see then you know
misformed embryos a lot of that we start
in the lab other labs to it too we sit
in nature all the time
where you get completely different um
uh outcomes in the morphology even
though not all of these occur because of
some genetic mutation that's not always
the case sometimes it's just basically
perturbation environment and the same
genetic code with some little
differences that here
is basically that the difference is here
between one simulation and different if
you did it that way we didn't but if you
did
at least not in this paper if you had
different randomization initially of the
prior beliefs you can also get different
outcomes but um even with one
randomization of of the initial beliefs
you will get certain outcomes for those
cell types based on um on the coding but
also what the environment does that's
the kind of the the goal is you have
cell types you have you want to see what
how can you change the line of cell type
differentiation based on an interplay
not just like saying you do that and you
tell the seller to this but based on how
they interact with each other
hope to answer your question
it makes me think of waddington's
landscape the epigenetic landscape which
i'll copy in how would you say it
relates to epigenetics or the epi
genetically
also if i have my shirt here i have a
shirt with it but i i don't see it right
now yeah i love the uh white instrument
in it yeah it's exactly um right so that
that was a the big
i love you big nap
i'll put it onto a slide
yeah
basically right the whole
the whole evolution was that initially
when we started understanding genetic
information that it was thought well
that that's that's the end of it now we
know where to be done here like we know
basically that there's some certain
signals that will be recessed and then
you will get certain genes but the thing
rolls down
um but basically just from that it's all
all straightforward what was new then
later on was the epigenetic part of it
that was basically actually
modifications happening not on the
like you did not notice mutations of the
genome but which genes were more or less
accessible for expression
which you know again so basically you
kept the coding the same but based on
modifications a lot of system
modifications right the the way that the
chromosomes where the dna is wrapped
around itself and chromosomes the more
or less tightly they are equal to each
other the more less accessible to
transcription factors
um and that started basically happening
later on instead and now we think a lot
more about this and we even see this
even that's even heritable
um and uh it's it's
it's also interactive with a lot of more
the physical forces of it so you know
perturbations in the in the mechanical
or bilateral environment
will lead to to a lot faster epigenetic
transformations of course it's not
faster it's also important to mention
that there's a lot faster process it's
faster to basically
modify some of the proteins that are
make up the histones and then make up
the accessibility of the genetic code
then to start off going some evolution
experiment where you start doing
mutating and cross over until you get
the right combination so it's a
different layer
of information flow that is interactive
with your negative level
um so
what this paper kind of interacts with a
little bit or you know intersects with
it is the aspect of of health
in that initial kind of information
where you have the same genetic code
within basically one lifetime
how do certain
modifications and in sensory precision
which you can think of right
i didn't make that explicit claim
i i hate to make claims that i'm not
actually then afterwards answering some
relevant biological mechanism but i
could think of easily that way that use
this these modifications of the the the
um the response function
um that the sense the sensitivity
of the of the double tail experiments
and the
mis
the reduced sensitivity and the cancer
initiation those can easily be thought
of as as you know short-term epigenetic
modifications and we do see that a lot
this happens especially in stress
environments and embryos and stressful
environments and beyond genesis
where where there's very quickly changes
that can lead to drastic outcomes and
it's it's thought of as a as a quick
response mechanism to two basic
perturbations and and it's involved as
co of course in cancer as well that's
that's well known
so that's kind of how
i would think about that just the
landscape here is can be thought of as
the variation of energy landscape in the
sense of like what different outcomes
you can get how how how quickly you
update your your probabilities based on
the changes in the environment
awesome thank you dean
when i was reading this i i was thinking
of a
company that i'm
invested in that has taken stem cell
derived isolates
because people have diabetes and they
have created
an environment to protect against the
perturbation so instead of
injecting those pancreatic cells
directly into the portal vein
they try to
they have we're working on trying to
sort of create the environment in which
the isolates
survive so it so essentially it's again
rather than looking
from the bottom up it's it's sort of
creating that
safe environment in which these isolates
can then carry out their function
and so that's what i was kind of
thinking about throughout when i was
reading your paper now i'm not sure if
that
again whether i was thinking of the
correct analogy but
but yeah um in terms of what the
pancreatic isolates can do depends on
their survivability so if you don't have
the right kind of
environment for that um they tend to die
or
worse they don't die they become
cancerous so it's kind of interesting
that
you're looking at it here and then i i
know of some sort of practical
application but the research is really
trying to
build these environments so that they
can actually protect against the
perturbations yeah no that's exactly the
long lines i'm thinking as well
i do i like two more minutes um if i get
the knife and go
um
really appreciated you joining
if it works for you to drop in or out at
any point in the dot 2 please feel
welcome and any other time you or anyone
else are welcome to participate but
thanks a lot for joining
you're welcome my pleasure
see you later
okay
bye
bye thank you
excellent that was great fantastic
great
yeah fun times
um okay so here's here's one thought on
the relationship with foraging kind of
picking up on what we were just looking
at
so
he described some of the
manipulations as kind of like
interventions that were epigenetic so it
wasn't the addition of
um
like another changing the model
structure like changing their from four
to five transcription factors
um
it was just
changing their state it's like picking
one cell up and moving it would be
changing its position but then there's
other levers of intervention like
changing its sensitivity or other
aspects of its cognitive or its
generative model
and the whole point with
science and active inference
though c anticipating brain is not a
scientist by broonberg's paper so it's
not exactly the same thing but it's
about informed
or directed experimentation
and that's true from the epistemic
foraging with the isocating to the
scientific
experiment
when we make targeted interventions into
systems
based upon
a good understanding of them
we can learn about the cognitive model
that's underlying it or the as if
cognitive model so there's a lot of
interventions that would not be
informative about morphogenesis like
jokingly you know hitting the petri dish
with a hammer it's it's an intervention
that does kill cells it kills cancer but
of course isn't that the joke right like
there needs to be more to it
in the experimental design and in the
the measurement of the outcomes so that
we're actually learning something and so
to make increasingly nuanced designs
and learn more and more and apply better
and better
that's where having like this kind of
formal modeling really matters so this
is kind of taking just saying like well
changes in receptors might be a
precursor or a biomarker or an early
mechanistic warning of x disease
you'll read that a hundred thousand
times in the molecular biology
literature and this is picking up there
and putting it into a modeling
architecture
where we actually can talk about changes
in signaling and position in an
integrated way
so that it might be able to actually
model real settings just like people use
the epigenetic landscape heuristically
but also increasingly quantitatively to
model selfie decisions but just to kind
of close that again it's the
interventions
that we as the investigator know based
upon our understanding of like the
natural history of the system
that
give us updates on our cognitive model
of the system so like an ant foraging
example is they'll take a desert ant
that forges
alone the decimate goes out without
following like just simply a pheromone
trail
and pick the ant up when it's like let's
just say 30 meters away from the nest or
10 20 meters away and then move it to
like 90 degrees rotated
the same distance
so
one extreme case would be it continues
from that location a hundred percent as
if it were walking back from the north
let's just say
that would be a pure direction step
integrator model
there might be
an angle it takes between that
and for example heading towards the nest
that might reflect the usage of other
sensory or cognitive features like
detecting the polarization of light or
scene memory or other ways that it might
be able to
adjust and turn its vector to some other
direction
so
that's the kind of experiment where
we can start to learn like how much are
the
nest mates in their foraging adjusting
between
their own onboard memory versus these
external cues that might be picked up
like in one instance by any nest mate in
that location
so there's some cells where moving it
into a different tissue the first thing
it would do is die
because it's just like too acidic or
just like not a good environment for it
but there are certain interventions that
do seem to happen
that lead to at the very least we can
say states we don't prefer
or just more directly like states that
are abnormal or unhealthy
though it really does come back all to
blue's question about death
and aging and
how is that related and
what is this living phase between the
developmental part
and the death part
even though there's such a complex
continuum between them
stephen
can i just ask a question on what you're
just saying there daniel um
do you feel that or do you think that
the um
the the level of what's happening with
epigenetics is fairly flat
and it and the once these other types of
changes these types of changes happen
that the adjacencies
permeate out and can
the the cells are kind of finding their
place
um
and is that a bit different to the
nestedness you know that we're talking
about the nestedness is
because um like for instance a tissue
or is that also
does it then fall into some other
type of um
behavior
where it's like into this idea of the
nested
um
the nested kind of markov blankets
and is it then a case of
what was
the types of information flows which
were conservation at one scale
have become noise
that makes sense so maybe
i'm just curious about
if that
is in here
um
it very well might i mean what it just
makes me think about is the eye
specification in
fruit flies and and similar in other
insects so this is like an example of a
developmental genetics pathway
at a relatively downstream level being
worked out
through a lot of work
but these cells are pre-committed
to being eye precursor cells but then
they undergo a second
or a future stage of differentiation
that results in a compound i and then
it's the modularity of this
developmental
framing of first i precursor cell and
then to a specified eye compound
cell
that lets like the insect eye scale in
different ways for example than the
mammal eye developmentally so over
evolutionary time there's different
affordances for insect eye evolution
versus mammalian cell eye evolution um
because they're on different pathways
so
it's kind of fractal because
this
eye field precursor it's not
the second one that comes out of the
embryo so
there's multiple
like fractal
layers and pre-committals
and it's not possible to jump from a
canyon way at the bottom
directly over there's a few cancers cell
papers that do a little bit more of like
a reversion and around or a perturbation
that pushes
and then changes to like susceptibility
or kind of like changes in the elevation
of these hills between
so it's a landscape
which isn't just simply flat
um it has some scale
and then
the
relationship between how jagged it is
and how much
noise or flow
there is is about how navigable that
landscape is
in that one model
blue
so i have a question for
daniel and dean specifically um so when
franz was here he talked about the block
matrix operator that he used in equation
and you guys well maybe it was daniel
specifically we're talking about some
kind of housekeeping term in the dot
zero and i couldn't remember or place
the housekeeping term that you were
referring to and i wondered if it was
like the same or similar in a similar or
used in a similar way
i think it's connor i'll bring in a
housekeeping
term slide it was from 32
live stream 32 stochastic chaos markov
blankets
and um
[Music]
here
is the slide in slide 45 here
yeah
it was um
basically
the helmholtz decomposition
is
usually discussed in terms of just the
gradient the solenoidal so sort of like
directed
term and then the iso contour
circulation change in elevation ruler on
the hill and then around the hill on the
isocontour
and then
this paper
brought in the housekeeping term
and then there was like a supplement so
we didn't really totally go into it but
together
um they represent the total flow so it's
a slight kind of
um fristen variation on the helmholtz
decomposition
in this context but as conor mentioned
in 32.3
it also has like sort of antecedents and
maybe even similarities with other areas
so totally remains to be a little bit
unpacked but it's the influence of how
movement changes the landscape
at least that's a little bit how we were
framing it like change on a trampoline
where the movement is going to influence
it you can't just snapshot the landscape
and then calculate what would happen and
what the gradient and the solenoidal
flow would be at every point because
it's going to be the future
well that might be related to what franz
was saying because he said he used it to
smooth out the landscape because
otherwise you get stuck in like a little
local pocket when you're talking about
like you know something that that's
bumpy so it sounds like it could be a
similar type of um like housekeeping
thing or just like a smoothing
smoothiness when you're when you're
going into the bowl you don't want to
get stuck in a bump down along the way
right if you're a marble traveling down
like i thought it was a cleanse
[Laughter]
there's just too many too many jokes to
be made um but
um
wow i think in our last you know
ten ish minutes we should just chill
land the plane prepare for dot two it
was pretty unexpected and awesome
to have the um
time that we got to speak and i think
that's like the housekeeping term in
action
which is a process and a protocol
and then people who have different
perspectives on a situation but the
group
can always re-adapt to a changing
landscape and so even if that's
interpreted as structure learning at a
higher level
from the sort of
agent view looking up
it's equivalent to adapting to a
different situation in some fractal way
slightly different or very different
using the same affordances and
perceptive and cognitive features as it
had in the time step before
and that's why
um
this
model
that looks at the flow of the autonomous
states
so um the states that can actually be
controlled in the markov blanket
partition
in 30
by defining a specific function that we
want to like be fitting well
by really focusing on the flow over the
blanket and internal states
it allows inference on that component
perception cognition and action
of the given modeled entity
to be
uncoupled in a certain way from
inference on
the hidden external state evolution
which is fundamentally unknowable but in
a slightly different way
if that makes any sense
and a classic moment blue to suggest the
the
mitotic elements
and like
just to bring in the continuity and then
the way that that gives rise to symmetry
breaking sort of for free
um and that this or and
[Music]
so it's
cool conversation that we had today and
so
so i ended up as a dot one might
i didn't get to mention that i was gonna
mention it um but like you know
there's that fractal
fmri brain pattern paper that i'm like
dying to read and
would love to discuss with the authors
also
but it's interesting just in terms of
the the fractal dimension also that
franz was talking about is super cool
um
is there anything else that we want to
like
um
write down to think about in the dot two
or questions that we would like to ask
franz if he returns or just things that
we want to
take moving forward in the dot 2 already
yeah i i agree it's like it's like
you're eating dinner it's like when you
want dinner tomorrow
inverting space and time we didn't
really get to um and some of these
initial points it was
right at least action math and
morphology and then
generalized flow and taking us all the
way back dean so i i would like to maybe
ask ask friends about quantum mechanics
and what
role if any that that played in um
like what is there a quantum perspective
that that he was
perhaps viewing in from
um when he was writing this paper i
would i would like to ask just that one
question because that will encompass
inverting space and time and it will
encompass
what we're talking about with the
probability current
and um the probability mass conservation
so like that all is like bridging into
the quantum where we'll go in the 40. so
i think i would like to ask about that
one thing
dean what are you like looking forward
to or would you want to add here at the
end
i'm just going to go back to the drawing
board and basically look look a little
more closely at some of those math
operations because i don't tend to give
those as much attention as i need to i
think it's really interesting uh
now that we've
had a chance to sort of
bring more people into the conversation
i think
of there's three parts to i think we can
agree there are three
things that we can really center on now
there's the
the formally form forming which is what
figure four and five do
but as soon as you go to figure five
what's interesting is is that the
the attention seems to be on the shape
that the
cells eventually take and yet in the in
the sort of in the blackness around each
one of those moment captures
there's
there's signaling and there's changing
right there's so there's all the part
we've talked about today which is the
whole flowing piece and what where is it
going and how is it channeling and how
is it narrowing or how is it spreading
and how is it dissipating and all that
stuff
but in those even in those diagrams it's
hard to figure out
where the signal is even when they
introduce arrows
they introduce the arrow pointing at
the form
not
the necessarily the signaling and the
changing and that's where the math
really comes in i think because
without the math you you lose sight of
those other two
present
factors that are you know
all
moving and mixing and and turning into
something
so
i hope
france comes back because
man he's got a heck of a lot more um
he's got a lot more to tell us about
really because this is such a dense
paper like i think i mentioned to you
daniel before before the point zero this
could be a 13 week course this one paper
if you really
wanted to i don't know how many hours he
spent on this but he already admitted
that going to carl's lab and and
and from the lab he's at there's way
more multiples of ten thousand hours of
work that we're done before he
started typing things out so
yeah
awesome what that
made me like think about is this idea of
like multiple kinds of invisibility or
overlay
or unpacking like projection up into a
bigger dimension of interpretation
like you pointed out how the sig like
the focus was on morphology which is to
say the final realize like this picture
is of the morphology of the animal it's
not of the signaling density but this
could be like presented as just a
gradient of transcription factor a
or it could be presented as a gradient
of vitamin a
or like it's kind of like krillian
photography
like looking at the morphology with the
energy field i don't know if that's
exactly what it is but that sort of idea
with the the field based perspective
but then it gets hard to show
many overlaying
fields
because like what do you do 20
overlaying colors but we we can't
actually see that and so that's just
kind of interesting like a question
about visualization of higher
dimensional models with a lot of
overlays and then
that's like one kind of invisibility
which is something that's modeled but
just not graphically shown easily like
the density of 50 pheromones or 50
transcription factors or vitamins
but then also but but it does exist and
it's like modeled as an actual chemical
component of the biological system like
the generative process
and then
there's this generative model with the
mathematical derivatives
the generalized coordinates of motion of
cellular position and those are also
like invisible in a different way
because they're
um
a modeling
tool
and the derivatives are not anywhere in
reality like what is where's the seventh
derivative of the baseball's movement
just
relative to what where is it hiding in
the current moment
this is just a purely
tool-driven way of thinking about the
current moment not just in terms of its
composition and like anatomy
and position and the lowest level of the
observed model but like these higher
levels which are
real yet
not existing in the moment
structurally real
in the
structural realism sense i'll take your
word for it
i've been wanting to say that for a long
time
i have to now go back and figure it out
so
um but
but uh discussion i hope like for those
who stick around to the end here that
they enjoyed this that this wasn't just
um
total uh
total
morpho apostrophe
all right well
fun times and awesome to have all the
good discussions and appreciate
everybody who
was here blue and steven and dean so see
you all next week or any other time
peace
bye thank you
you